A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia 1881-1919 (bulk 1901-1919)
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia 1881-1919 (bulk 1901-1919)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.472 III
This collection consists of ca. 6,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.)
Scope and Content Information
These files (ca. 6,000 items) constitute the major record series generated by Edwin Anderson Alderman, the first president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Contents List
- General Records 1901-1919
  - AMiscellaneous, reference to Albemarle Survey 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Academic Schools--Miscellaneous 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Council, reference to student indiscretions 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--General Correspondence 1916 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Investments 1915-1916 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Meetings 1915-1917 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Miscellaneous 1915 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Treasurer 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Bulletin 1915-1918 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Fund 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Secretary, reference to U.Va. European Bureau 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - American University Union in Europe 1919 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions (1 of 3) 1915-1917 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions (2-3 of 3) 1915-1919 (Box 2)
  - Art and Music (establishment of School of Fine Arts) 1915-1919 (Box 2)
  - Articles about UVa 1916 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Universities 1916 (Box 2)
  - Astronomy [1881]1915-1916 (Box 2)
  - Athletic Committee 1915-1918 (Box 2)
  - BMiscellaneous, reference to war issues; British Education Mission 1915-1918 (Box 2)
  - Barbour-Page Lecture 1915-1919 (Box 2)
  - Biblical History and Literature, reference to Christian Woman's Board of Missions 1915-1919 (Box 2)
  - Biology (including other earth sciences) 1901-1919 (Box 2)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Fraternity Houses 1916 (Box 2)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Land Leases 1916 (Box 2)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Landscape 1915 (Box 2)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Superintendent's Office 1915-1919 (Box 2)
  - CMiscellaneous, reference to the Chapel; College des Etats-Unis Paris; Corks & Curls 1915-1919 (Box 3)
  - Carnegie Foundation 1915-1919 (Box 3)
  - Chemistry, reference to burning of Chemical Laboratory, now Miller Hall 1911-1917, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Convocations 1915-1918 (Box 3)
  - D-F Miscellaneaous, reference to race issue; fraternities; Lee's tomb 1912-1919 (Box 3)
  - Economics 1915-1919 (Box 3)
  - Education, reference to death of Prof. Heck 1915-1919, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Engineering Department 1917-1919 (Box 3)
  - English, reference to Edgar Allan Poe Chair of English Literature; death of Professor Kent 1917-1919, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Entrance Requirements n.d. (Box 4)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships 1915-1919 (Box 4)
  - Finals 1914-1919 (Box 4)
  - Finance--Budget Statements 1915-1919 (Box 4)
  - Finance--Fees of Students; Return of Forestry 1916 (Box 4)
  - Forestry 1915-1919 (Box 4)
  - Forms 1915-1919 (Box 4)
  - Founder's Day 1915-1919 (Box 4)
  - G-H Miscellaneous, reference to entrance gates (gateway to U.Va.) 1915-1919 (Box 4)
  - General Education Board--Data on Schools of Education, Middle West Universities 1915 (Box 5)
  - General Education Board--Data on Schools of Education, Southern Universities 1916-1919 (Box 5)
  - General Education Board--Data on Schools of Education, Western University 1915 (Box 5)
  - Geological Survey 1917-1919 (Box 5)
  - Geology 1915-1917 (Box 5)
  - Gifts to the University 1915-1919, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - History 1915-1919 (Box 5)
  - Honor System 1916-1919 (Box 5)
  - Hopkins, W. E.--bequest 1915-1919 (Box 5)
  - I-J Miscellaneous, reference to income tax exemption 1915-1919 (Box 5)
  - Invitations 1916 (Box 5)
  - Instructors and Assistants 1915 (Box 5)
  - K-L Miscellaneous, reference to Latin America 1915-1918 (Box 5)
  - Legislative Program 1915-1919, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Library 1916-1917 (Box 6)
  - Loan Fund 1915-1916 (Box 6)
  - M-P Miscellaneous, reference to Panama-Pacific Exposition 1915-1919 (Box 6)
  - Mc Miscellaneous 1917-1919 (Box 6)
  - McConnell Memorial 1917-1919 (Box 6)
  - Mathematics 1915-1919 (Box 6)
  - Medical College Transfer 1915-1916 (Box 6)
  - Medicine--Anatomy, reference to death of Dr. Richard Henry Whitehead 1916 (Box 6)
  - Medicine--Clinical n.d. (Box 6)
  - Medicine--Hospital 1915-1919 (Box 6)
  - Medicine--Miscellaneous 1915-1919 (Box 6)
  - Medicine--Pathology and Bacteriology 1918 (Box 6)
  - Military Instruction--ROTC (1-2 of 7) 1917-1919 (Box 6)
  - Military Instruction--ROTC (3-7 of 7) 1917-1919 (Box 7)
  - Military--Student Army Training Corps (S.A.T.C.) 1918, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - National Association of State Universities 1917 (Box 7)
  - Philosophical Society n.d. (Box 7)
  - Philosophy 1915-1919 (Box 7)
  - Physics 1916-1919 (Box 7)
  - Political Science 1915-1918 (Box 7)
  - Psychology 1917 (Box 7)
  - R-S Miscellaneous, reference to race issues 1915-1919 (Box 8)
  - Rhodes Scholarship 1915-1917 (Box 8)
  - Romantic Languages 1917-1919 (Box 8)
  - Secondary Education 1915-1917 (Box 8)
  - Southern Education Board--Data on Schools of Education, Northern University 1915-1916 (Box 8)
  - Statistics 1915-1916 (Box 8)
  - Stokes Fellowship 1915-1916 (Box 8)
  - Summer School 1915 (Box 8)
  - Summer Work 1916-1919 (Box 8)
  - T-V Miscellaneous, reference to Troubetzkoy 1915-1919 (Box 8)
  - Teaching Staff 1917-1919 (Box 8)
  - Term Reports 1915-1919 (Box 8)
  - University Extension 1915-1919 (Box 8)
  - Visitors--Meetings, reference to burning of chemistry laboratory 1915-1918 (Box 8)
  - Visitors--Membership 1916-1919 (Box 8)
  - Visitors--Docket (14 June 1915) 1915-1916 (Box 8)
  - Visitors--Docket 1915 Nov 3 (Box 8)
  - Visitors--Docket (1916 April 18) 1915 Nov-1916 Apr (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket 1916 Jun 12 (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1916 October 19) 1916 Jun-Oct (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1917 March 16 and April 16) 1916 Oct- 1917 Mar (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket 1917 Apr 19-20 (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1917 May 31) 1917 May- Jun (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1917 September 28) 1917 Aug- Sep (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1917 November 27) 1917 Nov- Dec (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1917 December 28) 1917 Sep- Dec (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1918 March 27) 1918 Jan-May (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1918 June 10) 1918 Apr- May (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1918 November 26) 1918 Feb- Nov (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1919 March 4) 1918 Dec-1919 Apr (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1919 May 1) 1919 Mar- May (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket (1919 June 10) 1919 Mar- Oct (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket 1919 Oct 14 (Box 9)
  - Visitors--Docket 1919 Nov 21 (Box 9)
  - W-Z Miscellaneous 1915-1918 (Box 10)
  - Woman's College 1915-1919, 4 folders (Box 10)